<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The beginning and progress of a needful and hopeful reformation in England with the first encounter of the enemy against it, his wiles detected, and his design ('t may be hop'd) defeated.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15155</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11924098</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11924098</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beginning and progress of a needful and hopeful reformation in England with the first encounter of the enemy against it, his wiles detected, and his design ('t may be hop'd) defeated.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus). Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51003:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51003:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BEGINNING AND PROGRESS OF A Needful and Hopeful REFORMATION IN ENGLAND. WITH The Firſt Encounter of the Enemy againſt it, His Wiles Detected, AND HIS Deſign ('t may be hop'd) Defeated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51003:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51003:2"/>
            <head>To the King.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT I have written ſo plainly as I have done, of Matters ſo much concerning your ſelf and your own Actions, was not for any want of Affection either to your Perſon or Cauſe, nor yet through any inſolent Humour; but from great Affection to your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, great Concern for the happy Succeſs of your Majeſty, in your not only juſtifiable, but commendable and honorable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings; and above all, Fidelity to God, who, I was ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, had raiſed you up; and whom I deſired you might follow Faithfully and Fully, as thoſe happy Captains of old: But I ſoon perceived you, to my great Grief, to be in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be miſlead, and I took the moſt effectual Courſe that I could to prevent it, that you might be ſenſible of it in time.</p>
            <p>This I did as an Honeſt Man, a Loyal Subject, and a Faithful Friend to my Country: But now I can with ſome Aſſurance and Confidence ſay ſomething more; that the Hand of God was in it; I have had Experience for the time of four Apprenticeſhips, of the unhappy Conſequences of ſuch a Miſcarriage of my own, in a Caſe, wherein few or none, that I know, were likely to have directed me better. And I have been trained up for near as long in ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of Fidelity to my neareſt and deareſt Relations and Friends, which were at the time no leſs troubleſome to my ſelf than ungrateful to them. But theſe are things I little thought on, till not long ſince, knocking at one of their
<pb facs="tcp:51003:3"/>Doors, (where I had been once an intimate and a welcome Gueſt, but upon ſuch an occaſion for many Years after a Stranger,) all this matter was very clearly opened to my mind; and ever ſince I have been very ſenſible that there was a ſpecial Hand of God in it all, from my firſt ſpeaking to your Highneſs (as then it was) at <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> my drawing the Declaration after at <hi>Henley,</hi> and all that I have done ſince; though I knew it not; only I had the Comfort of my Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Fidelity to God and Man. And what I wrote at firſt, but conjecturally concerning the Perſons and Counſels, which have miſlead you, Time and the ſpecial Providence of God, have ſince confirmed, and given me clearer Evidence of it.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Age</hi> is thought by many to be as Learned and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ever any was: for my part I know none that I think more conceitedly Ignorant: Learned in Languages, in Books, in Notions and Opinions of Men, in Sophiſtry, and the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Ornaments of Learning; Skillful in diſhoneſt Craft, which they call Policy; and experienced in the Anatomy of Sublinary Creatures; I eaſily grant: But for the <hi>Interiora Rerum;</hi> intimate Acquaintance, and Spiritual Senſation (as one calls it not amiſs) in the Great things of Religion, Profound <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in true Wiſdom, and Knowledge of the Powers of Nature, in theſe I take it to be very ſhort. And for particular Perſons, I doubt there are few equal to ſome who have lived in Ages reputed the moſt Ignorant and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned. As for Religion I know very well, and can ſay it with Confidence, that both the Conformiſts and Non-conformiſts are all inexcuſably Faulty in the External part of it; and I doubt will be found as defective in teaching and inculcating ſome of the moſt important Doctrines of it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Internal. The <hi>Reformation</hi> was a neceſſary. Work, and the Work of God; but Men have carried it on with too much of a Humane Spirit of Oppoſition; which hath, indeed, caſt out many Abuſes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſeems to have left them divers excellent Virtues, and
<pb facs="tcp:51003:3"/>other good things to themſelves. This hath cauſed the Fruits of the Reformation in all parts to be ſo Mean and Barren, and every day more and more dwindling, till almoſt all was, by degrees, over-run with Ambition, Covetouſneſs, Senſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, and at laſt with Atheiſm, Infidelity, Prophaneneſs and Debauchery, and Contempt of all Religion. And for the great and important Matters of Religion, many great and learned Men of this time, ſeem no better to underſtand and uſe the New Teſtament, than the great Doctors of the Jews did the Old in our Saviours. And where Religion is ſo defective and ſuperficial, I am certain there can be little of Profound Wiſdom. Nor do I admire at this at all; for I ſee very few, who take the right way to attain it, but moſt many ways run from it: Firſt, in purſuit of the Profits and Preferments of the World; and when they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them, by the uſe they make of them: And beſides all this, the vulgar Learning of the World, as it is uſed and purſued, is as great a Diverſion as any thing I know: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that in thoſe Matters one may more eaſily meet with ſound Advice and Direction from a ſincere, religious, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Chriſtian, that is well acquainted with the Sacred Scriptures, and a Book or two of Devotion, and no more, than from any of our Phariſaical Doctors, who look Huffing and Big, and with empty Oratory and Sophiſtry, draw igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant conceited People after them. And I dare confidently affirm, that diligent Study, and conſcientious Obſervance of the Canonical Scriptures, the Books of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> and <hi>Tho. à Kempis</hi> his Chriſtian Pattern, ſhall make a Man not only a better Chriſtian, but a wiſer Man even in the Management of Civil Affairs, and the Buſineſs of the World, if he apply himſelf to it, than all the Syſtemes of Divinity, Ethicks, Oeconomicks and Politicks, and all the Learning beſides, that this Age hath produced, without the true Power and Spirit of Religion. I value Learning and learned Men, as much as any Man doth, if it be joyned with ſolid Virtue: But among learned Men, I
<pb facs="tcp:51003:4"/>ſee many, who are meer Drudges for the Wiſe, only they gratifie their own Humour; and thoſe I pitty, to ſee them ſo near Wiſdoms Gates, and not to find the Entrance: But others, who are Cheats, and having firſt corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived themſelves with the Shells and Superficials, or ſome mean part of Learning, or Skill, are very dangerous to be relyed on for their Judgment, in Matters which require the beſt Advice that can be.</p>
            <p>I have once before touched upon this by way of Caution, when I did only, though ſtrongly, <hi>ſuſpect</hi> that your Majeſty might ſuffer ſome Inconveniencies by ſome miſtaken Counſels. But I now write more Freely and Confidently; becauſe <hi>now</hi> I <hi>know</hi> that it hath been ſo; and I ſhould be heartily Sorry that it ſhould continue ſo longer. I know the Affairs of your Majeſty have been from your firſt Acceſs to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here, greatly prejudiced by the Evil Counſels of ſome Men, and I know the Men, ſome of them at leaſt. I know your Affairs have been greatly prejudiced both here and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond-Sea; and if you remove not ſome Perſons further from you, and caſt ſome ill Mem from your Favour, you will meet with many Rubs and Difficulties, and your End will be Inglorious. You have been miſlead into the rough and crooked Ways of the Wilderneſs, (which I underſtand very well by many Years grievous Experience;) and led out of the plain and happy Way of <hi>Abraham.</hi> You came into this Land under the Hand of Divine Bleſſing; but you have fallen from that State, and ſince been only in a State of Mercy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. The Work of God indeed hath gone on, and muſt go on, and you may be made uſe of in it, but you will meet with many Croſſes, and miſs of your Aim, in what concerns your ſelf, unleſs you can recover your former State; which though not Impoſſible, I have found to be very Difficult, and intelligent and faithful Guides in ſuch caſes rare to be met with. The great Doctrine of <hi>Repentance</hi> is corrupted, and abuſed by the Papiſts; and it is imperfectly, nay and falſly, taught amongſt the Proteſtants: (I make no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb facs="tcp:51003:4"/>whether Conformiſts or Non-conformiſts.) There is a neceſſary and an indiſpenſable part in many caſes, and many times when the Sin is ſecret, that is, <hi>Giving Glory to God,</hi> which I have hardly ever known mentioned, but never treated by any to purpoſe. The Ancient Chriſtians under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it well; the S. Scriptures expreſs it by doing <hi>Works meet for Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Judging our ſelves:</hi> But the Spirit of Oppoſition hath almoſt ſuppreſſed it amongſt us, and thereby betrayed many Poor Souls; ſo that the Neglect thereof cauſeth them to lye long, it may be all their days, under the Judgments of God; which might be avoided, if this Doctrine was truly taught, and Wiſely and Faithfully Practiſed.</p>
            <p>Such a Judgment I have mentioned in the following Tract upon your Majeſty; the mention of which to the Counſels of Fleſh and Blood may ſeem to expoſe your Majeſty, and ſtrengthen the Hands of your Enemies; but the Truth is not ſo; for it will have a quite contrary effect, unleſs the Fault be in your ſelf. It was mentioned for the Glory of God, and for a neceſſary Admonition for your own Good; for the Conviction of thoſe who have miſlead you, that ſeeing their Error, they may be ſo much the more concerned that you may be ſet right; and for the Conſideration of thoſe who deſire to be Faithful to you: And if you humble your ſelf under the mighty Hand of God, give Glory to him in owning his Hand in it, and apply your ſelf reſolvedly to Works meet for Repentance, he will certainly raiſe you up above all your Enemies: Nay, your Humiliation and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of his Correction, is the firſt ſtep of the only ready way to recover your ſelf, and gain an Augmentation of your Honor. We all are Spectacles, not only to Men, but alſo to the Angels, but ſuch eſpecially as are called or lead to any ſpecial Service; and if They do not actually Glorifie God in the Works to which they are called, there are thoſe Miniſters of his, who will ſecure his Glory in the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Judgment upon them, <hi>until they know that the
<pb facs="tcp:51003:5"/>moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of Men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will.</hi> But this is not all, the next ſtep is the Works of Repentance, Eminent Acts of the contrary Virtue to what hath been done amiſs, ſteadily pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued with great Reſolution, upon all juſt Occaſions. And ſuch an Occaſion is now offered in the Matters related in the following Diſcourſe, which may prove of evil Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to be either neglected or lightly put off. It is true, the Honor and Authority of her Majeſty, which ought to be as dear to you as your own, is concerned in it; and the Honor of your own Adminiſtration no leſs. But you are to look beyond all this. It is more properly (and indeed indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) your Office to be Active and Magnanimous in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Laws, and the due Execution thereof, than in Fighting our Battels. That is the part of a General, this of a King: And this is properly that, wherein you are Gods Deputy and Vice-gerent. And the Faithful Performance of the Charge of this Relation to him, is always to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded far above all Tranſitory Honor and Temporal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations whatever; and doth often require a greater Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity, than to charge an Enemy in the Field. This may be done by a Brutiſh Courage, wherein an Engliſh Maſtiff is equal to the greateſt General in the World; but that is peculiar to Man, and to the Noble Creatures above him: And to the Faithful Performance thereof, a generous Magnanimity is ſo requiſite, that God himſelf preſcribed it as a neceſſary Qualification in his Judges. And to this, if I be not greatly miſtaken, your Majeſty is ſpecially, and doubly obliged, as Matter of Duty, and as one of thoſe Works I have mentioned before.</p>
            <p>But this is but one of them, it is not a bare Execution of the Laws, that thoſe Obligations of yours extend to, but a Vigorous and Magnanimous Proſecution of the Ends of theſe Laws, which is the Suppreſſion of all Wickedneſs and Impiety, by all the Means, wherewith by Law you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted; by which Virtue and Piety may be encouraged, and
<pb facs="tcp:51003:5"/>Vice and all kind of Wickedneſs diſcouraged and ſuppreſſed. To conquer the Vices of a Nation is a more glorious Work than to conquer their Armies: And this is to be done more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by reſolute and conſtant Demonſtrations of your Favour and Diſpleaſure towards the greateſt Perſons of the Nation, as they deſerve, than by the ſtricteſt Execution of the Laws, were they ſeverer than they are, againſt thoſe of meaner Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, without it. And if you have not Zeal enough, nor Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity enough, nor Courage enough, nor true Wiſdom enough, to do this generouſly and reſolutely for the Honour and Service of God, the Good of the People committed to your Charge, and the Satisfaction of a good Conſcience, your Religion is vain, your Courage bruitiſh, and your Wiſdom Fooliſhneſs with God, (not to ſay Earthly, Senſual and Deviliſh) and God will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly lay your Honour in the Duſt, ſhould you ſo neglect His for Fear of Man; which always brings a Snare. He is in truth not a King, but a Slave, or hath little Eſteem for Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that wants either the Power or the Will to have Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons only to attend upon himſelf, or the Perſon of his Queen. He is not fit to be a Biſhop, or Superintendent of the Congregations of a City, who cannot order his own Family; much leſs is the fit to be a King, who cannot model his Court according to his own Mind. The leudeſt of Men even Common Souldiers, may be reclaimed by Diſcipline; and are thereby reſtrained from thoſe Enormities, to which they have greater Temptations than to Swearing, and other Sins which Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity prohibits. And where they are not, Experience proveth it is for want of real Vertue in their Commanders. Much more may thoſe, who often appear in a Prince's Preſence, if the Prince hath Piety enough to deſire it heartily, and Manly Magnanimity enough to try it to purpoſe. If in ſuch a Cauſe as this King <hi>James</hi> had ventured his Crown, he could never have loſt it; for God and Man would have been for him. And this muſt be done now, if it was more dangerous than it is; ſome eminent Acts of this nature muſt be done, before the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer proſperous State can be recovered; And more than this; for there is no ſuch Danger or Difficulty in it, as ſome vain Politicians would pretend.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51003:6"/>
            <p>The firſt regard in all our Actions ought to be to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, from whom we have our Being, upon whom we do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and to whom we owe and muſt give Account of all our Actions, and of the Employment of all our Powers and Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Oportunities for his Service. The next regard, but ſubordinate to that, is to be to the Good of <hi>Man:</hi> And this our Gracious God accepts as a principal part of his Service: It is in effect the ſame which <hi>Daniel</hi> recomends to the King, as a proper Means to recover the Favour of God and avert the Judgment decreed againſt him. <hi>Wherefore, O King, let my Counſel be acceptable unto thee; and break off thy Sins by Righteouſneſs, and thine Iniquities by ſhewing Mercy to the Poor.</hi> Ambition of Domination, and wilful Encroachments upon the Rights of others, is abominable in the ſight both of God and Man, and mightily aggravate any former Offences, eſpecially when under Correction. But when theſe things are really aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and it is manifeſt by a conſtant courſe of Actions, or ſome ſufficient Demonſtration, that the Honour and Service of God, and the Good of a People is ſincerely and principally intended, this engageth both God and Man to favour ſuch a Perſon. And this I dare ſay with great Confidence, and without any partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, on behalf of <hi>my own Country,</hi> that there is not a Nation under Heaven that naturally produceth a braver People, or more eaſily governed by a Wiſe, Juſt, and Generous Prince than this; a People more Faithful, more free of their Purſe, or more Couragious in any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking. Let them but enjoy their Rights, and they are eaſily pleaſed; but they are naturally honeſt, and plain-dealing, as generous Minds always are; and abhor tricks and underhand Practices, which have been the common, if not only Politicks of the late Reigns. This and maintaining Favourites, who have been the Maſters and Inſtruments of ſuch Policies, have made the Government uneaſie to the People, and the People to appear otherwiſe to the apprehenſions of Strangers, than their Natural Genius realy is, when all proceeded from the Imprudence of the Princes, and the Baſeneſs and Corruption of ſome Evil Men, who most ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily inſinuated into their Favours, by ſuch Arts and indirect
<pb facs="tcp:51003:6"/>Means, as the Genuine honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Genius diſdained and could not brook.</p>
            <p>And now Sir, If you will follow their Methods, and make uſe of their Inſtruments, you muſt beware how you diſoblige this and that Lord and their Parties; for the People ſeeing you ſet up a ſeparate Intereſt of your own againſt theirs, and to enrich your ſelf and a Party of corrupt diſhonest Favourites, make uſe of the old Arts to pick their Purſes and cheat them of their Subſiſtence, they will be ready to cloſe with any in the proſecution of the means of their Relief; as they did with your ſelf againſt the like Practices of your Predeceſſor. But if you be reſolved to demonſtrate your Vertue and Magnanimity, for the Honour and Service of God; first in conſtant effectual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging and ſuppreſſing of all Prophaneneſs and Debauchery, and encouraging Vertue and Piety (which is agreeable to the Engliſh Genius naturally diſpoſed to Religion;) and next (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing thoſe former vulgar Policies, and rejecting thoſe few Vermine and Beaſts of Prey, which thoſe degenerate Reigns had foſtered and bred up) in acting only upon the plain and eaſie genuine Engliſh Principles of true Policy, Juſtice, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Induſtry; maintaining the Rights of the People, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Delinquents (though otherwiſe the greateſt Favourites or uſeful Miniſters) to the clear Juſtice of the Laws; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torting nothing by indirect Means, but retrenching needleſs and exceſſive Salaries, Penſions, and Expenſes; craving nothing but upon juſt and evident occaſions, and imploying it according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the common Benefit of the Nation; making thoſe things, which are in truth your proper Charge and Buſineſs, your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and greatest Care, Endeavour, and Deſign; theſe Means will certainly give you that Favour and Power with God, and that Empire and Command in the Hearts, Purſes, and Actions of this People, that will ſet you far above all Temptations to mean Compliances with vicious Perſons, be they never ſo great and powerful; or any Faction whatever at home; and make you a Terror to your Enemies abroad.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Direct Way</hi> to all this is plain and eaſie to be found, if carefully heeded and obſerv'd; but ſo different from the vulgar
<pb facs="tcp:51003:7"/>Tract of Policy and Wiſdom of the World, that it cannot but ſeem Folly and Madneſs to ſuch <hi>Abderites.</hi> It requires only a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Attendance to the End, and an Heroick Magnanimity, to walk ſteadily in it. Theſe two make that Noble Vertue ſo much extoll'd in Sacred Writ, which overcomes the World. If the Heart be pure, and the Eye fixed upon the End, the Way will eaſily be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and then if there be true Magnanimity to proceed, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there can be no compleat Vertue) no Monſters of Menor Devils can hinder the Progreſs, but ſerve only to make the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements the more Glorious: Yet ſuch there are which muſt be encountred and ſubdued, and the moſt dangerous of all the very firſt, that Monſter of <hi>Self,</hi> which is the Devil in Man, and will certainly play the Devil indeed, and confound all, if not throughly caſt out, and carefully watched and kept out Other wiſe it will defile the Heart, divert the Eye, and by ſome <hi>Ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus</hi> miſlead a Man out of the true Way, the only Way of God's Bleſſing; and then he certainly falls into the hands of ſome of the other Monſters, who are permitted to worry him till he recover the right way again. But if this first be caſt out, and conſtantly kept out, the reſt will eaſily be vanquiſhed and put to ſlight, and have little Power to hurt him. Of thoſe, ſome are eaſily known by their monſtrous Horns, Ears, Eyes, Tongues, Talons, Tales, cloven Feet and filthy Odor; and a noble Here may ſubdue them by his ordinary Retinue: But there are others the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous becauſe, though in truth as very Monſters as the reſt, they can pull in their Horns, and ſo diſguiſe themſelves, that a Man may be in danger, and be damnified by them before he be aware: They are of the Nature of <hi>Foxes</hi> (or Wolves in Sheeps-Cloathing) <hi>Syrens</hi> and <hi>Remoras,</hi> and they are to be ſubdued by the Here himſelf, or by a Band of ſelect Champions. The ſubduing of all theſe at home (which is not hard) would make your Conqueſt of all abroad eaſie, your ſelf a Glorious Inſtrument indeed, and theſe Nations Happy. Which is the only aim in all this, and the hearty deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Humble and Faithful Subject</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51003:7"/>
            <head>THE BEGINNING and PROGRESS Of a Needful and Hopeful REFORMATION, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>NOthing can be ſo well and commendably done, but the Wit and Malice of Evil Men, through the Inſtigation and Aſſiſtance of the Apoſtate Spirits (who rule in the Minds of all ſuch, and carry them captive at their Will) is able to miſrepreſent it as evil, blame worthy and deteſtable. Nor ever was, or can any thing be well undertaken, and begun for the Glory and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite of Almighty God, the Honour of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the Good of Men; but it alway hath, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will meet with all Oppoſition poſſible, by thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, Powers and Wicked Spirits, with whom we contend in thoſe unhappy Subjects of their Empire of Darkneſs, in whom they really act, riding them as an Ape a Maſtiff-Dog, though their proper Reſidence be in the vaſt Regions of the Air. And when mortal Men undertake any ſuch real Good Works upon their own Head, in their own Strength pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming upon that, or other plauſible Work for their own Glory, though under the Self-deceit of a better Deſign, without the Preſence and Aſſiſtance of the Inviſible Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Divine Providence, and out of their Conduct,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51003:8"/>though with never ſo great Appearance of Humane Power and Ability, they are eaſily baffled and over-power'd, and their Work defeated, if not turned to the Diſadvantage of what was propoſed. But when the Work is of God, though the Beginning be never ſo ſmall, the Means never ſo difficult, the Inſtruments never ſo weak on unlikely, it muſt ſtand; and the Gates or Ports of Hell; that is, in the Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, the Grand Seſſions of Devils, with all their ſecret Councils and Cabals, and all their Power, ſhall not be able to prevail againſt it, or defeat it. It is true, wicked Men ſhall have only a Temporal Reward for their Service; and thoſe who do not fully follow the Divine Conduct, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeek their own Glory more than the Glory of God, or yielding to the deceitful Counſels of Worldly Wiſdom neglect what is moſt for his Honour and Service, ſhall be blaſted, and loſe the Honour they might otherwiſe have acquired: But the Work ſhall go on and ſucceed notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and all Oppoſers be cruſhed and oppreſſed, and deceitful Workers confounded. This is ſtrange Doctrine and new Philoſophy to the Sentiments of this degenerate ſenſual and brutiſh Generation: But it is in it ſelf notwithſtanding old, true, and certain. And whoever they are, who either in publick or private Affairs, act without due regard to thoſe Inviſible Powers, they act but as Brutes, Fools, and People in the dark, though they may ſeem to be very ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in many reſpects: for never was any conſiderable thing done in the World, without the Interpoſition of ſome of thoſe Powers. Of moſt of this ſome Inſtances may be obſerved in what follows.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> was no ſooner invited to the Adminiſtration of Affairs in this Nation, than he was to the exerting of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and the Reputation and Advantages, which God had given him, toward the moſt neceſſary Work of a <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of that Wickedneſs, and thoſe abominable Impieties, which had overſpred the Nation, and provoked the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt his Predeceſſors, that he might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51003:8"/>ſecure the Bleſſing of God upon his Adminiſtration: But it is not ſtrange, if where Chriſt had his Meſſenger, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil had his Miniſters, <hi>Elymas</hi> like, to pervert the Right Ways of God, and turn away his Deputy from the Faith and Belief of thoſe things, which were ſo neceſſary at that Time and Seaſon. And though the ſame Neceſſary Work hath been divers times, upon ſpecial occaſions, much preſſed ſince, yet nothing hath been produced by that means, unleſs that <hi>Letter to the Biſhops,</hi> which commendable indeed in it ſelf, yet was ſo defective in reſpect of what ought to have been done, that it may juſtly be feared, that it had no better Acceptance with God than it hath had Effect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men to this purpoſe. True <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have for many Ages been little regarded in Princes Courts; but for the moſt part been miſrepreſented and excluded by Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, Flatterers, and the Maſters of vulgar Politicks, not to ſay Pimps and Panders, and the moſt diſſolute, licentious, and worſt of Men. But though the Evil Counſels, which for ſome time have prevailed, and intercepted from the King that Honour and Succeſs, and from the People thoſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, they might before this time otherwiſe have enjoyed, were long ſecret; yet by the ſpecial Providence of God they have ſince appeared in publick: And it may be hoped, as it is our Duty to pray, that God will, notwithſtanding all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Errors, yet give their Majeſties underſtanding to diſcern the vaſt difference there is between True Wiſdom, and the Evil Counſels of ſuch Vulgar Politicks, both in the Event and in the Principles.</p>
            <p>The ſame Neceſſary Work hath alſo been propoſed <hi>to the Parliament,</hi> but there ſtop'd and ſuppreſs'd, by the mean Prudentials of ſuch as ought to have been, in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the moſt generous and zealous Promoters of it: But as ſince that time the Good Providence of God, and the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Majeſty hath ſupplyed us with ſome Perſons, from whom we may expect better things, ſo that Good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God hath not been wanting to his own Work in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51003:9"/>other reſpects; and from a ſmall Beginning, will, I doubt not, carry it on to Perfection, through all Oppoſition, and to the Confuſion of all, who ſhall dare either openly or ſecretly to give any interruption or diſturbance to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of it.</p>
            <p>About this time the laſt year, the Officers and Inhabitants of the <hi>Tower-Hamlets,</hi> upon occaſion of their Majeſties Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation for the apprehending of Highway-men, Robbers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> conſidering that Common Bawdy-houſes were the uſual Nurſeries and Receptacles of ſuch evil People, reſolved to uſe their utmoſt Diligence and Endeavours to ſuppreſs the ſame; and for that purpoſe, drew up an Agreement in Writing under the Hands of many of them, which was afterwards proſecuted with very good Succeſs. And this was remotely the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of another Agreement, of which I ſhall give a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account, as followeth:</p>
            <p>One of theſe Subſcribers, coming afterwards to live in the <hi>Strand,</hi> recommended this, and propoſed ſomething of the like Nature to a Gentleman, whom he believed to be ready to embrace and promote any good Propoſals for the Benefit of his Country; and who thereupon propoſed it to ſome other Gentlemen of his Acquaintance, whom he thought had Leiſure, and were well affected to ſuch Works; who likewiſe readily embraced the ſame. And they all agreed to meet once a Week, not at any certain Place, but ſuch as from time to time they ſhould think moſt convenient, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſome ſuch Undertaking, and to promote it what they could.</p>
            <p>But thoſe Gentlemen being all but one private Perſons, and living in ſeveral Parts, and not likely to be conſtantly Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Inhabitants about <hi>London,</hi> could not conveniently engage in any ſuch Pariſh-work; but leaving that to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the ſeveral Pariſhes, thought ſomething of a more univerſal Nature, and ſuch as private Perſons by their Pains and Purſes might promote, more proper for them: And thereupon began to conſider how they might beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51003:9"/>the <hi>Execution of ſuch Laws,</hi> as we have <hi>againſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Prophaneſs and Debauchery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And conſidering that all this Miſchief, which like a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent had overſpread the whole Nation, and all Ranks and Degrees of People in it, proceeded indeed from the evil Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the late Reigns; but yet received great Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Remiſsneſs and Negligence of the Magiſtrates and Iuſtices of the Peace, in not duly executing the Laws, as by their Oaths they are obliged to do: This appear'd a Difficulty above their Power to overcome, and for which no proper and effectual Remedy could be thought on below Her Majeſty's Authority.</p>
            <p>It was then not long before a General Seſſions was to be held at <hi>Hicks-Hall</hi> for the County of <hi>Middleſex;</hi> and Her Majeſty was no ſooner moved for her Letter, to recommend and require the ſtrict Execution of thoſe Laws, to the Juſtices there; then ſhe did moſt readily and graciouſly receive the Motion, and commanded a Letter preſently to be prepared as full as might be for that purpoſe. And as well for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Inſtance of her Piety and Vertue, as for the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of it, and relation it hath to the Buſineſs in hand, I think fit here to inſert it, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>Maria R.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>TRuſty and Well beloved, We Greet you well.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſidering the</hi> great and indiſpenſable Duty <hi>incumbent upon us, to promote and encourage</hi> a Reformation of the Manners <hi>of all our Subjects, that ſo the Service of God may be advanced, and thoſe Bleſſings be procured to theſe Nations, which always attend a Conſcientious Diſcharge of our reſpective Duties, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ſeveral Relations, We think it neceſſary, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the obtaining of this Publick Good,</hi> to recommend <hi>unto you the putting in Execution, with all Fidelity and Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, thoſe Laws, which have been made, and are ſtill in force againſt the</hi> Prophanation of the Lords Day, prophane Swearing and Curſing, Drunkenneſs, <hi>and</hi> all other <hi>lewd, enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51003:10"/>and diſorderly Practices, which by a long continued Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and Connivance of the Magiſtrates and Officers concerned, have univerſally ſpred themſelves, to the Diſhonour of God and the Scandal of our Holy Religion; whereby it is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the more neceſſary for all Perſons in Authority, to apply themſelves with all poſſible Care and Diligence to the ſuppreſſing of the ſame. We do therefore hereby</hi> charge and require <hi>you to take the most effectual</hi> Methods <hi>for putting the Laws in Execution, againſt the Crimes above mentioned, and all other Sins and Vices, particularly thoſe which are most prevailing in this Realm; and that eſpecially in ſuch caſes where any Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Justice ſhall be guilty of any of thoſe Offences, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe or neglect to diſcharge the Duty of his place for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing them, that ſo ſuch an Officer by his Puniſhment may ſerve for an Example to others. And to this end we would have you be careful and diligent in</hi> encouraging all Conſtables, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, Headborroughs, <hi>and all</hi> other Officers and Perſons <hi>whatſoever, to do their part in their ſeveral Stations, by time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and impartial</hi> Informations and Proſecutions <hi>against all ſuch Offenders,</hi> for preventing thoſe Judgments, which are ſolemnly denounced againſt the Sins above-mentioned. <hi>We cannot doubt of your performance hereof, ſince it is a Duty to which you are obliged by Oath, and are likewiſe engaged to the diſcharge of it, as you tender the Honour of Almighty God, the flouriſhing condition of his Church in this Kingdom, the continuance of his Holy Religion among us, and the Proſperity of the Country.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>And ſo we bid you farewell.</salute>
                     <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>White-hall,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 9th. <hi>day of</hi> July, <hi>in the Third Year of our Reign.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>By Her Majeſties Command. <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>To our Truſty and Well-beloved the Juſtices of the Peace for our County of <hi>Middleſex as Hicks</hi>'s Hall.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51003:10"/>
            <p>This was the Letter, and, beſides others afterward, it had this happy Effect, or Conſequence, at leaſt, immediately following: In bord date the Ninch of <hi>July;</hi> the Tenth it was delivered to the Juſtices; the Eleventh they made their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der purſuant to it; and the very next day, it is obſervable, had we that famous <hi>Victory in Ireland;</hi> as if the Almighty, who by his Wiſdom diſpoſeth the Times, Seaſons, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of all things, deſigned that very time for the Engagement, (which, as I take it, neither party then intended,) to demonſtrate or ſignalize his Favour upon ſo ſmall a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a Reformation.</p>
            <p>No doubt but ſome, who think themſelves wiſe, will ſmile at leaſt, or ſhake their Heads, at this Obſervation. But they muſt know, that it is not <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> but often folly and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, not to take notice of ſuch Minute Things, as the Vulgar (even of learned and reputed Wiſe Men) little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. And though from ſuch Circumſtances conſidered alone it may not be fit to be very poſitive in concluding ſuch Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences; yet from a concurrence of divers Circumſtances, a truly Wiſe Man may receive ſuch ſatisfaction for the happy and ſucceſsful guidance of his Actions, as the <hi>Wiſdom of the World</hi> is not capable of. And the Truth is, <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications</hi> are for the moſt part rather by ſuch ſecret Hints and unobſerved Admonitions, as the wiſeſt of Worldly Men would over-look, than by ſuch ſenſible Incitations as might move a Horſe or a Mule; though even ſuch are often overlooked by many who think themſelves wiſe, and too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſuch as are in ſome degrees Partakers of the true Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Wiſdom. <hi>Becauſe they regard not the Works of the Lord, nor the Operation of his Hands, he will deſtroy them, and not build them up:</hi> But, <hi>whoſe is wiſe will ponder theſe things, and they ſhall underſtand the Loving Kindneſs of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore paſſing by former Occurrences, upon this Occaſion I think fit to add here a brief Obſervation upon ſome of <hi>this Year.</hi> In the War in <hi>Ireland</hi> His Majeſty was concerned in Intereſt more than in Honour; becauſe he was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51003:11"/>not engaged in Perſon in it, and it was not managed under his immediate Conduct. But in the Common Cauſe of the Confederates he was more concerned in Honour, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally engaged in it. A Noble Confederacy it is indeed and a Juſt and Honourable Cauſe; and it hath been bleſs'd with no mean Succeſs in general. But if we conſider the Particulars; though there hath been nothing wanting, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Courage, Activity or Conduct in the King, and he had a great and powerful Army under his Command; yet hath he ſo failed in Succeſs, that he hath been able to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all. <hi>Ireland</hi> hath been reduced without him; the Emperor's Forces have had ſuch Succeſs againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> when they were more in danger to have been deſtroyed by them, than to have obtain'd ſuch a Victory, that the <hi>Turks</hi> have been forced to a Truce: And thoſe in <hi>Savoy</hi> have had the like, forcing the <hi>French</hi> General to retire into his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Territories. But thoſe under the immediate Command of King <hi>William,</hi> have been like the bewitched Cart, I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly mentioned, and been able to effect nothing at all; but on the contrary, he ſuffered ſome Diminution of his Honour at the beginning, by the loſs of <hi>Mons</hi> almoſt before his Face; and ſome alſo, in concluſion, by the <hi>French</hi> falling upon his Rere. I know that ſhort-ſighted Men can eaſily ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſome ſuppoſed viſible Cauſes of all this. But whatever they think, theſe things are ordered by a ſecret Hand of Providence; which no Man, who hath any true Senſe of Religion, can deny. What then may be the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this, in relation to that over-ruling Providence? I will not ſay again what I have ſo often ſaid; and ſince a third Years Experience hath now confirmed what I ſaid at firſt. It is true, the Work of God doth, and muſt go on, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; and he hath, and, I believe muſt ſtill have, for ſome time a great Hand in it; but, I doubt, unleſs he be better adviſed, and take better Counſels, it will be but of Service, not of Honour; that part will be given to others: <hi>Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> (as it was ſaid to <hi>Barack) the Journey that thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51003:11"/>ſhall not be for thine honour,</hi> Jud. 4.9. Which words have been much in my mind this Summer. And there is beſides a farther danger, leſt what he hath gained already he may not longer enjoy than is neceſſary for this Service. I write not this to prejudice his Majeſty or his Service; but in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Faithfulneſs to him; and that both he himſelf, and thoſe about him who are well acquainted with the Main Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, and heartily deſire his Well-fair, may be moved to take theſe things, and the Queſtions not long ſince publiſhed into ſerious conſideration, and diſcern wiſely what is to be done. But he muſt have a care whom he truſteth: for the caſe is not eaſily diſcerned by every Doctor; much leſs how hard it is, when a man is once ſurpriſed, to get out of it; and what are the moſt abſolutely neceſſary Means in order thereunto; And He hath been too much deceived and miſlead already.</p>
            <p>This is no impertinent Digreſſion from what I was about, for his Majeſty is equally concerned in what follows, as well as what goes before, and they are nearly related the one to the other. And therefore I now proceed: The buſineſs by her Majeſties Favour ſucceeding ſo happily, theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men farther conſider'd, that if the Juſtices ſhould be as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to iſſue out their Warrants according to their own Order, as they had been to paſs their Order in purſuance of her Majeſties Letter, yet that could have little effect, unleſs people could be prevailed with to give due <hi>Information</hi> of the Offences every where committed againſt the ſaid Laws, as they ſhould have occaſion to know and take any ſpecial notice of them. And for that purpoſe they agreed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade as many as they could, not onely to give Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all ſuch Offences of this kind as they occaſionally ſhould take notice of; but moreover, as their leaſure ſhould permit, to go out into the Streets and Markets, and publick places on purpoſe, and to obſerve the peoples behaviour there; and of ſuch Offences as they obſerved to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt any of the ſaid Laws, to give information to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51003:12"/>ſome Juſtice of Peace at their next leaſure. And a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable number they prevailed with to doe this, merely out of a commendable Zeal for the Honour of the Chriſtian Religion and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and a juſt Abhorrence and Deteſtation of thoſe unmanly and wicked Abominations which are every where committed to the offence of all who have any ſpark of true Religion, Vertue or Conſideration in them; they being all of them perſons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſuch as frequent the Prayers of the Church and the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in ſo populous a place, and where Impiety and Wickedneſs was grown ſo impudent, the Informations againſt ſuch Offences daily committed were like to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for the Eaſe of the Juſtices of the Peace in iſſuing out their Warrants (for which no Fee is to be paid to their Clerks) leſt it ſhould become tedious to them, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neglected, theſe Gentlemen, at their own charge cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Blank Warrants to be printed, for all ſuch occaſions, and beſides provided and imployed fit perſons in ſeveral parts of the City and Suburbs to fill up the ſame, as the caſe ſhould be, for any who ſhould be willing at any time to give Information thereof to any Magiſtrate or Juſtice of the Peace: ſo that the Juſtice had ordinarily no more to doe but to examine the perſon upon his Oath, and ſign and ſeal his Warrant, unleſs there might be occaſion for any little alteration in it; and the Informer had a much eaſier diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch than formerly, when he muſt attend the leaſure not onely of the Juſtice himſelf, but of his Clerk too, till he could have leaſure to draw his Warrant, whch was often a great diſcouragement to him to trouble himſelf another time.</p>
            <p>This done, unleſs the Juſtice would pleaſe to take the trouble upon himſelf to ſend the Warrant to the proper Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer (which he ought to doe, and could command no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy but his own Servant to doe it) to eaſe him alſo of this trouble, it was ordered that the perſon who ſhould give
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51003:12"/>the Information, ſhould be deſired to bring back the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſigned to him that fill'd it up. And another perſon was imployed to call weekly for all Warrants ſigned and ſealed by any Juſtice of the Peace, and then to carry them out and deliver each of them in the ſeveral Pariſhes to ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Officer of each Pariſh where it ſhould be executed. And for this they allowed him out of their common Stock half a crown a day.</p>
            <p>And leſt the Buſineſs after all ſhould receive any diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment by the Neglect or Miſcarriage of the Officers to whom the Warrants ſhould be delivered, the perſons depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to fill them up were ordered to keep an Account of the ſeveral Offenders, the Offences, the time and place of the Commitment; and of the reſpective Juſtices of the Peace who ſhould grant the ſaid Warrants; and he who was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to carry them out, was likewiſe ordered to keep a like account of the reſpective Officers names to whom he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them, to the intent that <hi>Regiſters</hi> might thereby be made of all to be delivered to the Juſtices of the Peace at their P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y Seſſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ſeveral Diviſions, to enable them the better to examine the Officers how they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted the ſeveral Warrants delivered to them, and to charge them to account for the ſeveral Penalties by them levied.</p>
            <p>Having thus ordered natures about theſe parts, they far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſidered how they might promote this happy begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to other parts of the Nation; and to that end and purpoſe cauſed the Order of Seſſions for <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and the like Order of the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen to be printed in a ſmaller letter, and to be ſent into all parts of the Nation, it their own charge, hoping that other Cities and Counties would thereby be provoked to follow ſo good an Example, and ſhew their readineſs of themſelves to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie her Majeſties ſo gratious and pious intentions: As the County of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and that City did, having timely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, the ſame Quarter Seſſions: and others, 'tis ſaid, have done the like ſince.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51003:13"/>
            <p>This was a Buſineſs which they foreſaw from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning could not be carried on without ſome Charge; and therefore for that purpoſe they preſently agreed to raiſe a <hi>Common Stock</hi> by their own voluntary Contributions. And though they reſolved to ſpare neither Pains nor Coſts, for the promoting of it, yet being moſt of them private perſons, they thought it moſt prudent upon diverſe conſiderations to manage it with as little noiſe as might be, and with all the <hi>Privacy</hi> that a buſineſs of this nature is capable of. And had continued ſo to doe, had not the Malice, Miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and Calumnies of ſome evil perſons, at <hi>this laſt Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions at Hiks's-Hall</hi> made a <hi>Plain Narrative</hi> of their Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings neceſſary for a Juſt <hi>Vindications</hi> of their Innocent, Honeſt and Commendable Deſign and Undertaking.</p>
            <p>It is true, it could not be expected but that many <hi>Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> who were puniſhed by the Juſtice of theſe Laws, would be incenſed againſt all ſuch as they ſhould know to have any hand in promoting the Execution of them, as likewiſe ſuch <hi>diſſolutes </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are unwilling to be reſtrained within the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Religion, Vertue or Sobriety. And it has been obſerved that many ſuch as are <hi>ill affected to the Government,</hi> have at much as any oppoſed and exclaimed againſt this Execution of theſe Laws, principally, and with the greater heat and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe recommanded and required by her Majeſties Authority. But there being nothing in all thoſe Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings contrary to Law; or which any private perſon might not lawfully be concerned in, but all deſigned and directly tending to the promotion of what her Majeſty had ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly recommended and required for the Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and the good of the Nation, there could be no doubt of the Apprebation, of her Majeſty and of a good people, if it ſhould at any time come to be known. And it was all ſo contrived for the Eaſe of the Magiſtrates and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace, that upon that ſingle conſideration it might well be thought to deſerve not onely their Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51003:13"/>but Thanks alſo and ſpecial Encouragement: But there are two other Conſiderations in the Caſe, which ingenuous minds would have been ſenſible of, and affected with: the one, that what was done, was for promotion of their own Order; the other, the Honour that was done them by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending their Example to the whole Nation. And great pity it is, that a Party of unworthy perſons gotten into the Commiſſion of the Peace of this County ſhould have ſo far prevailed upon ſome of their fellows, as by their Raſhneſs and Inconſiderateneſs, (to ſay no worſe,) to bring a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh upon the Bench, where notwithſtanding (to doe them right) were many worthy perſons, who utterly diſliked their Proceedings, beſides many others of worth and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty who were abſent.</p>
            <p>It is certain that no part of the Nation doth more abound with perſons of worth and well qualified for the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice than this part of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> near <hi>London:</hi> and yet it is commonly ſaid and believed, that it hath uſually had the unappineſs to have more notorious, corrupt, merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and ill men in Commiſſion of the Peace than any County of <hi>England</hi> beſides. And the reaſon may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be this. Hither is the common reſort of the dreggs of the whole Nation, and (beſides many other vicious and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious people) of many perſons of broken fortunes, and many Lawyers, who have neither Abilities to get into practice, nor Vertue to be contented with their own Eſtates, and what they might honeſtly acquire by ſuch employments as they are qualified for. And whereas in other Countries there is nothing of Profit to be eaſily gotten by being in Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Peace, which might invite any to ſolicit to be in, but a certain Charge attending it; in this it is commonly ſaid and believed, that ſome Juſtices of the Peace do uſually make 200 or 300 <hi>li. per annum</hi> of their places, or more. And it is not unlikely, if it be well look'd into, that there may be, found at this time in Commiſſion of the Peace for this County diverſe perſons of very ill Morals, of profane
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51003:14"/>and light Converſation, of decayed and broken Fortunes, and ſome profeſſing the Law, who have little or no Practice, unleſs as Juſtices of the Peace, and who have uſed great ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation by recommendations to get in; and ſome who may reaſonably, and are ſuſpected to be no good and faithfull friends to this Government. And from ſome of theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, probably, the violent Oppoſition that hath been lately made to thoſe honeſt and commendable Endeavours of the Gentlemen before mentioned for promoting her Majeſties Pious and Honourable Intentions, and the very End of the Order of Seſſions, hath proceeded.</p>
            <p>Though the Order of Seſſions upon the Queen's Letter was paſſed without any interruption and with great expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the very next day after the receipt of the Letter, and and in like manner ſuch an other Order in the City by the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen not long after, though without any ſuch Letter to them directed; yet it ſoon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that ſome <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the City, and <hi>Juſtices</hi> in the County were <hi>not ſo forward</hi> to obſerve their own Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and execute the Laws as was expected. This appeared by the treatment, which divers met with; who offered to give them Informations, but were put off, checked and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged for their pains. And it was obſerved that ſeveral who were moſt cold in the buſineſs were ſuch as were belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not overwell affected to the Government: And this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned thoſe <hi>Queſtions</hi> which were printed in <hi>the Athenian Mercury,</hi> Sept. 5. which are not improper to be here inſerted, as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether an Alderman in the City, being a Juſtice of Peace, or other Juſtice of the Peace in the Countrey, refuſing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke an Information upon Oath againſt any ſcandalous Sin or Offence puniſhable by the Law, and ſubject to his Cognizance, or to ſend out his Warrant for the Puniſhment thereof; upon legal Convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth not thereby violate his Oath of Juſtice of Peace, and become guilty of Perjury before God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51003:14"/>2. <hi>Whether for that Cauſe, eſpecially if his Refuſal be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and notorious, though it be not puniſhable by the Statute againſt Perjury, he may not be puniſhed by the Common Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether it be not a plain indication that ſuch a Perſon hath little or no ſenſe of Religion, or of the Fear of God in his Heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether, it being plain Matter of Fact, that many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the late King</hi> James <hi>are ſo far tranſported with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that they not onely refuſe to obſerve our Solemn Faſts, but oppoſe the Reformation of the manners of the Nation, in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Queen's Authority recommending the ſame, ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal as aforeſaid be not an Indication that ſuch Aldermen or Juſtices are no better Friends to the Government and Nation, than they are to Religion and Vertue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Whether it be not fit that their Majeſties be informed, and that they both out of Duty to God and Care for the good Government of the Nation, take Notice of ſuch Perſons, and not ſuffer the Execution of the Laws to be longer intruſted with them?</hi> Or, <hi>Whether the Government of a Nation may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the Execution of the Laws to ſuch inferiour Magiſtrates, as may be juſtly ſuſpected to be neither well affected to Religion nor to the Government?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Whether it be not the Duty of all good Chriſtians, and of all ſober People, who wiſh well to their Countrey, to Note ſuch Perſons, and to eſteem them as Heathens and Publicans, or no good Friends to their Countrey or the preſent Government, and to avoid them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were Queſtions one would think, no man who had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Knowledge in the Laws, or Affection to Religion, Vertue, or Sobriety, could be offended at; yet were there ſome Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices at a petty Seſſions, not long after, who were ſo much concerned at them, and had ſo little diſcretion, as to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their defect in both by great heat and warm diſcourſes, to have the Mercury ſuppreſſed, and when they knew not how to doe that, to have the Authour of them bound to his good behaviour, if they could know who he was, (yet was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51003:15"/>he one not hard to be known, and who never diſowned his own acts.) And theſe ſort of men, no doubt, readily ſtruck in to give ſome check to theſe Proceedings.</p>
            <p>But when diverſe of thoſe who were perſuaded, and out of a pious zeal for the correction of that Profaneneſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery which they frequently met with, reſolved to give Information thereof, found ſuch cold Entertainment and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements from ſome, they firſt applied themſelves to, their good Affections to ſo neceſſary a Work ſuffered them not to deſiſt for thoſe diſcouragements, but rather to ſeek out for other Juſtices of the Peace, where they might have better Treatment and an eaſie Diſpatch to return to their own employments, being moſt of them Tradeſmen. And when they met with this from ſome others, but eſpecially from Mr. <hi>Ralf Hartley,</hi> a ſober, vertuous and generous perſon; they daily more and more reſorted to him; ſo that in ſome time there were ſome hundreds of Informations brought to him, and upon due Examination he granted his Warrants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. But ſuch was his Caution to keep within the bounds of the Law, that his houſe being within the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the City, if any came to him to his houſe, he always refuſed to act any thing of Juſtice buſineſs there, but direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to ſome place in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> as his occaſions lead him, where they might come to him, and that once known more came to him.</p>
            <p>Among ſo many Informations, it were a wonder if no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntary Miſtakes were committed: yet it ſeems they were ſo few that Malice it ſelf could find out no more than two that carried colour enough to ground a Calumny upon: and two poſſibly there were; the one, The Owner of a houſe, and his Tenant (they ſay he was) lived both in the ſame houſe, which is an Ale-houſe: ſo that many might not know which of them kept the Ale-houſe. But if there was any miſtake in this, it was an involuntary miſtake: but the houſe was truly aſſertained in the Warrant: the other, A Woman, who buried her Husband, married another, but yet
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51003:15"/>being commonly called by the name of the firſt, as is frequent, ſuch as had not heard of his Death might well ſuppoſe him ſtill living. And this, if it was ſo, was ſuch another Miſtake as the former; but neither of them any fault in the Juſtice. And yet theſe are all the Faults that are particularly aſſigned in theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; which is a great Evidence of the Injuſtice of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies raiſed againſt him.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>one thing more,</hi> which hath been made uſe of for a Ground, and very Artificially dreſſed up into a fine Story, though it be in truth no more than this. One day there came to Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> to his Houſe a Perſon, whom he knew not, about ſome Warrnts: Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> being buſie, and before reſolved not to meddle with any ſuch Buſineſs there, ordered him to come to him to <hi>Lincolns Inn</hi> to a certain Chamber, where he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be at a certain Hour, and where theſe Gentlemen divers times met, but at this time were only Mr. <hi>Hartley,</hi> Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Y.</hi> the Owner of the Chamber. When the Man came there, he proved to be a <hi>Conſtable</hi> of the Pariſh, where Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> lived, of whom Sir <hi>R.</hi> had heard great Complaints for Misbehaviour and Neglect of his Office; and meeting him ſo Opportunely, reproved him for it, and threatened to have him puniſhed if he did not mend his Manners, as any one elſe might have done, without perſonating a Juſtice of the Peace. Beſides this one Conſtable, there was never any at that Chamber with any of theſe Gentlemen, but one, whom Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> once ſent for to ſecure a Drunken Man, who with a naked Bagonet frighted the People as they went along the Fields, and was by ſome of them brought before him there. And theſe were all the Conſtables that were ever there. Nor had Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> ever ſigned more than two Warrants at that Chamber, or any War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants at any other Chamber in <hi>Lincolns Inn</hi> above twice or thrice, when theſe Matters were ſo miſ-repreſented the laſt Seſſions.</p>
            <p>This is the Truth, the full Truth, and nothing but the Truth, of all the Matter which a <hi>Combination</hi> of ſome Juſtices of the Peace at a Publick Seſſions at <hi>Hick</hi>'s-Hall, have lately Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, Falſly and Scandalouſly miſ-repreſented in a Formal <hi>Order of Seſſions,</hi> under pretence of an <hi>Information</hi> to the Court, and in a <hi>Report</hi> of a Committee (to whom this mighty matter was by the Order referred to be examined,) grounded upon Oath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51003:16"/>(as they ſay) of I know not whom, I know what I ſay. This Language, though it may ſeem ſtrange to ſome, is no more than is neceſſary and decent in this caſe. Wherein the Perſons intended behaved themſelves not with that Gravity, Juſtice, Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, Candor and Integrity which becomes Judges and Magiſtrates; but as ſome little, peddling, mercenary Lawyers uſe to do; who if they happen to get ſome little brangling Cauſe, think they do bravely well, if in the opening of it they can but ſet it out with Colours, feigned Aggravations, and little Strains of Wit or Oratory, though for want of ſollid Matter and good Evidence upon the Tryal, it redound to their own Shame, and the confounding of their Cauſe. Juſt ſo have theſe Men done, to the expoſing of their own Wants both of Religion, Virtue, Law, good Manners and Diſcretion, and to the Scandal of the whole Bench and Commiſſion, and deſerve no better but to be treated by all Men with Indignation and Contempt, as will more fully appear hereafter. But in the mean time, that they took their ground from that one Paſſage betwixt Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> and that Conſtable, may be preſumed from theſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that it was at that Chamber, that Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hartley,</hi> and the Owner of the Chamber were all three there at that time, and they only, which did not often happen, there being other Gentlemen beſides, who did uſe to meet, and not always there, upon the ſame occaſion, not one of whom, it ſeems, their Worſhips had any notice of.</p>
            <p>Some Gentlemen undoubtedly were drawn in to concur very innocently in theſe things, through the confident Pretences of others of the Informations they had received; and though ſome others might readily concur out of Prejudice againſt the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of thoſe Laws: yet that which at firſt ſeemed to move the greateſt Heat, was <hi>a Suppoſition of ſome conſiderable Profit,</hi> which thoſe Perſons, who were at ſuch Charge, and took ſuch Pains, muſt certainly put into their own Purſes. And great talk there was of the Ways how it might be done, doubtleſs by ſome, who better underſtood the Trade, than the Office, of a Juſtice of the Peace, and were diſpleaſed that any ſuch Advantage ſhould be intercepted from themſelves, by ſuch as were not in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Peace, and therefore had no Pretence for it. And it ſeems, and is very likely, that this Buſineſs was conſulted, and a Party prepared for it before the Seſſions, who thereby got
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51003:16"/>Advantage to carry it with the leſs Difficulty: But this Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the Seſſions, when better conſidered, was found ſo void of all Evidence or Probability to ſupport it, that we find nothing of that now either in the Report or Order preceding, though it was much talked on at the beginning of the Seſſions. But <hi>the Order of Seſſions,</hi> which bears date <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. runs in this Form:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This <hi>Court, being</hi>
                     </hi> informed <hi>that Sir</hi> R. B. <hi>Bar. hath ſet up</hi> an Office at <hi>Lincolns Inn in this County, to</hi> ſuperintend <hi>the Actions of their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for this County; And hath cauſed ſeveral</hi> Orders and Warrants <hi>to be</hi> printed <hi>without lawful Auoho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſo to do; And</hi> by the Aid of <hi>Ralph Hartley</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                     <hi>one of their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for this County, hath cauſed</hi> ſeveral Convictions <hi>to be made againſt ſeveral Perſons within the ſaid County</hi> contrary to Law, <hi>doth think fit, and accordingly</hi> Order <hi>that</hi> &amp;c. [the Names of the Twelve good Men are ſpared, though it be more than ſome of them deſerved.] <hi>Juſtices of the Peace, or any three of them be, and they are hereby deſired to</hi> meet, <hi>at</hi> Hicks<hi>'s</hi>-Hall <hi>in this County on</hi> Tueſday <hi>Morning next, and examine into the Truth of the ſaid Information; and by what Authority the ſaid pretended Office is ſet up and managed? and by whom? and to what end and purpoſe? What Inhabitants of this County hath been committed of any, and what, Offences, by colour and means thereof? and to certifie their</hi> Opinion <hi>upon the whole matter unto this Court on</hi> Friday <hi>next. And it is</hi> further or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>by this Court, that the ſeveral High</hi> Conſtables <hi>within this County do forthwith Summon the Petty Conſtables within their reſpective Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to bring into this Court, on</hi> Thurſday <hi>Morning next, all ſuch</hi> Warrants <hi>as remain in their Cuſtody for the Levying of any Summ or Summs of Money upon any of the ſaid Inhabitants upon any Convictions for Tipling, expoſing of Fruit or other Goods to ſale on the</hi> Lords day, <hi>or any other Offence for the Prophanation thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And for prevention of any</hi> Irregular Proceedings <hi>in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Conviction of ſuch Offenders for the future, this Court doth</hi> recommend <hi>it to the reſpective Juſtices of the Peace of this County, in their ſeveral Diviſions, to Summon ſuch Offenders before they be convicted of any Offence, and to inform ſuch Offenders of their Accuſers, and Offence of which they are accuſed; and not to convict any Perſon in his Abſence, unleſs after ſuch Summons he neglect or refuſe to appear before the Juſtice according thereto: And that no Juſtice of the Peace of this County do convict
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51003:17"/>any ſuch Offenders out of his own</hi> Diſtrict; <hi>nor diſcharge any Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders convicted of any Offence at any Petty Seſſions held out of his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but that it ſhall be left to the Direction of the Juſtices of the Peace within the Diviſion, where ſuch Party is convicted, to admit ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Bail, if they find it convenient.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Per Cur. Harcourt.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>How</hi> this Court was informed, or by <hi>whom,</hi> I find ſo hard to learn, that I vehemently ſuſpect there was no ſuch poſitive <hi>Information</hi> ever given in Court at all. However, the firſt part of it is falſe, and contains no leſs than a triple Falſhood: 1. That there was any ſuch Office: 2. That there was any ſet up by Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> 3. That there was any for any ſuch End, to inſpect the Actions of the Juſtices: The ſecond part is diſingenuous; for both the Orders and Warrants are known to be ſuch, as, though they had had no ſpecial Authority for Printing them, needed none; and therefore an Evidence of Diſhoneſty and Injuſtice in thoſe who promoted it, and pen'd or directed the Order, and of great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertence at leaſt in all that paſſed it. And the third an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and Fooliſh Calumny, Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> having more than once upon conſiderable Occaſions, given undeniable Evidence of his Conſtancy and Steddineſs to his own Principles and Conſcience, and therefore a further Confirmation of the Iniquity of thoſe who inſerted it, and of no leſs Incivility towards their own Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and of like Inadvertence at leaſt in all who conſented to the Paſſing of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Order</hi> of Reference had been reaſonable, if the Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had been fair and probable, and the Perſons named indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and impartial. But the contrary of this may be ſuſpected, ſince the Information being ſo faulty, yet all but one ſubſcribed the Report, which was referred to any three of them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Order plainly diſcovers how well affected theſe Gentlemen are to the Obſervation of <hi>the Lords day,</hi> and what regard they have to any Laws, which ſuit not with their Humour. For the Warrants concerning that, are the only Warrants, which they call in to Inſpect and Suppreſs.</p>
            <p>It alſo as plainly diſcovers what ſenſe of Religion they have, of the Honor of God, and of the Good of Human Souls; and whoſe Servants and Agents they are. Prophanation and irreverent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51003:17"/>uſe of things Sacred is a diſreſpect to God, and a pleaſant Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle to the Devil. And the Apoſtate Spirits, as often as they fail to draw Men into Evil, do preſently apply themſelves either to diſtract them with Buſineſs and Cares, or to divert them with Pleaſures and Recreations from that important Good, which cannot be attained by ſuch as ſeldom attend to it with ſerious and deep Meditation, but eaſily lay that aſide. And for thoſe whoſe Minds are all the ſix days incumbred with many things of the World, to be diverted a good part of the Seventh from that One thing neceſſary, cannot but greatly gratifie thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Spirits; and to ſee ſo much of their Work done to their hands; nay, and the very Miniſters of God for the Good of Men (as Magiſtrates are ordained to be) become Voluntiers in their Service for the Promotion of it, contrary to their Oaths, and contrary to the Laws, they were appointed to execute. I doubt there will be few found to have been very ſound Chriſtians, who have little regarded the Obſervation of this Day. And certain I am, that one of the Beſt and Wiſeſt Juſtices that ever <hi>England</hi> had, the late Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hale,</hi> was a very Religious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of it himſelf, and did greatly recommend it to others up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, both by Word and Writing, and largely in his laſt Inſtructions before his death to his Grand-Children, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Principles, Authorities, and Arguments of Reaſon, but alſo from his own long and frequent Experience.</p>
            <p>They conclude this notable Order with certain <hi>Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to their fellow Juſtices, (which is the third and laſt part of it) and with great appearance of <hi>Juſtice and Equity;</hi> but in truth with great <hi>Preſumption</hi> againſt the Laws, great <hi>Inſolence</hi> againſt her Majeſties Recommendations and Commands, and great Artifice to fruſtrate or obſtruct the Effect thereof, and of that very Order of Seſſions, which was made in Obedience and purſuant thereunto. Nothing can have a more plauſible appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Reaſon and Juſtice than the Prevention of <hi>Irregular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,</hi> and <hi>Notice</hi> of one's <hi>Offence</hi> and <hi>Accuſer</hi> before Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And by the Common Law no Man can be Convicted but after Summons and Tryal <hi>per Pares.</hi> But if the Wiſdom of the Great Council of the Nation have thought fit in ſome ſpecial Caſes, of notorious common Offences againſt the Laws, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Nation, but of God and Nature too, and for which the Penalties are ſmall in compariſon of the Crimes, to omit both,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51003:18"/>and to appoint a <hi>more expeditious way</hi> of Proceeding, it is a very bold Preſumption in a little Faction at a Seſſions to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wiſer than the Laws, and to aſſume to themſelves ſo much of a Legiſlative Power, as to preſcribe to their Fellows Rules to act by contrary to the Laws, and to correct the Methods dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Laws as <hi>Irregular Proceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like Preſumption it is to <hi>preſcribe narrower Bounds</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Fellows to act in, under a new name of <hi>their own Diſtrict,</hi> than their Majeſties and their Commiſſion hath ſet them, or their Oaths will allow them to obſerve. It is true, for Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Ale-houſes, and taking Accounts, and making of Officers, and ſuch like things, which cannot ſo well be done by Strangers, as by thoſe who live in the ſame Diviſion, the Juſtices in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have uſed (as by Law they may) to divide both the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the Profit, (which in thoſe things accrue to their Clerks) between them, and to act in their own Diviſions; neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can they ordinarily do otherwiſe, unleſs they would neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their own, theſe being matters which are uſually diſpatched in all the ſeveral Diviſions throughout the whole County at the ſame time. But it is a new Project to extend this to the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Offenders, thereby to hinder the Execution of theſe Laws. And ſuch is that of <hi>acquainting all Offenders who are their Accuſers,</hi> which would certainly deter People from giving any Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (the Penalties being ſo ſmall) againſt the moſt notorious, malicious, impudent, and deſperate Offenders. A much more juſt and reaſonable Courſe was it therefore, which Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> took, to let any one know who was his Accuſers, if he would be bound to Proſecute him.</p>
            <p>Theſe being matters of very bold Preſumption againſt the Laws, and greatly to the hinderance of the Execution of them, are ſo much the greater <hi>Inſolence againſt her Majeſty,</hi> who by her gracious Letter had recommended and command the ſtrict Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them with ſo much Earneſtneſs, as may be ſeen before.</p>
            <p>But this is not all; Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> Morning according to this Order <hi>the Counſtables brought in the Warrants</hi> remaining in their Cuſtody for the Offences aforeſaid, of which no ſmall number, had been neglected to be Executed, probably by ſome ſecret un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand Encouragement, and by theſe Gentlemen were torn or ſuppreſſed, under pretence of Illegality and Irregularity; by which, what they underſtand may be judged by what hath been obſerved already.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51003:18"/>
            <p>And here, having ſeen before how obſervant they are of the Laws of the Land, and of her Majeſties Recommendations and ſtrict Commands, it is fit to take a little notice <hi>What juſt regard they have to their own Rules and Preſcriptions;</hi> which they no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er make than they notoriouſly violate; unleſs they were made only in favor of ſuch as Tranſgreſs the Laws, which the Queen requires to be Executed, but not in favor of thoſe, who worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavor to promote the juſt Execution of them. Which is the Caſe of Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> a Gentleman of Quality, a Bar. who came over with the Prince, and a Perſon of very good Reputation: yet was not he vouchſafed this Favor to have ſo much as a Summons, or any civil Notice from their Worſhips.</p>
            <p>Nay, though upon a general Notice from others, That his name was in queſtion there for what he had done in this matter, he ſent a very civil Letter with an Abſtract of the Methods of the Proceedings before related, and ſuch a Regiſter of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants as is before deſcribed to Sir <hi>C. L.</hi> the firſt Man of the ſaid Committee, to give them all the Satisfaction that upon ſuch ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Notice was cenceived requiſite, and theſe were all deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by a Gentleman of good Quality before the Report was made, yet would the ſaid Sir <hi>C. L.</hi> and his Fellows needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in that raſh, ungentile, falſe and ſcandalous Report notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; as if there had been no Authority in the Nation to ſuperintend or control their Actions. Nor could he obtain the favor to be by them informed of his Accuſer, or of the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of his Offence, that he might have given a more particular and complete Satisfaction, if there was occaſion, before he was ſo ſcandalouſly miſrepreſented by the Committee in their Report to the Bench, notwithſtanding the Recommendations of their Order aforeſaid for that purpoſe in the caſe of any of the fouleſt Offenders without Exception. Which is plain Demonſtration that it was not any ſincere regard to Juſtice, but under Pretence of that an evil Deſign to obſtruct and diſcourage the Execution of theſe Laws, contrary to the Queens Letter, and to the Order of Seſſions thereupon, that was intended by ſome of them in thoſe Illegal Recommendations. The Letter was as followeth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51003:19"/>
                  <head>October 16. 1691.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOraſmuch as the Malice of Wicked Men has ſo far prevailed as to miſrepreſent that Undertaking in which, with divers worthy Perſons I am happily concerned for promoting the Execution of the Laws againſt Prophaneneſs and Debauchery in conformity to your Order of Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and on that account have not ſpared to calumniate me: I judged the true Repreſentation of this matter to be ſo neceſſary, that I have prevailed with thoſe Gentlemen to permit me to lay before you the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods they take in that Affair. By which it will manifeſtly appear, that it is ſo far from being Profitable, that it has been, and is no ſmall Charge to them. And in order to ſpread this yet further they have been moved to ſet the Example of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Middleſex <hi>before the reſt of the Kingdom, which required the Reprinting of ſeveral thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of both Your Orders, which have been by them ſent throughout the Kingdom, and of which they have already ſeen the happy Effects. And foraſmuch as all your Examination of Conſtables, as to the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Warrants, cannot but be defective, ſince you have no Account wherewith to charge them: Theſe Gentlemen have here alſo ſent you an exact Account of all the Printed Warrants which have been grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the very firſt, (except the laſt Fortnights which are not yet Regiſtred, but will be againſt your next Petty Seſſions) by which you may call every Conſtable to an Account for the Execution of the Warrants, which have been delivered to him. Which Account was deſigned and prepared for the ſeveral Petty Seſſions where they judged the Examination thereof moſt proper to be taken, had not this Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation forced them to a Vindication at this time.</hi> I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed> Your moſt Humble Servant, <hi>R. B.</hi>
                     </signed> For Sir <hi>C. L.</hi> Theſe</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51003:19"/>
            <p>By this Letter it appears that thoſe Gentlemen knew then of no other Calumny raiſed againſt them at the Seſſions, than that of making Profit to themſelves by this Undertaking; which they ſo fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that we find not any touch of any ſuch thing in the Report. And this, and what any prudent and ingenuous Man might have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved upon the Letter and other Papers, might have ſatisfyed their Worſhips (had they been ſuch) how little credit was to be given to the reſt, which the bare Truth of the Caſe hath ſo far confuted, though thoſe innocent Gentlemen were not permitted to know what they were. Of the which, that the Reader may judged ſhall here inſert <hi>The Report.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE, whoſe Names are ſubſcribed, in purſuance of an Order of Referrence to us hereunto annexed, have made</hi> diligent <hi>Inquiry and examined into the particulars to us referred; and upon the whole matter our Opinions are, Firſt, it</hi> appearing <hi>to us</hi> upon Oath, <hi>that there is, and for ſome months last paſt has been, an Office or Society kept in</hi> Lincolns-<hi>Inn, commonly called Sir</hi> R. B<hi>'s Office in the Chamber of Mr.</hi> Y—: <hi>And that there does</hi> preſide <hi>Sir</hi> R. B. aſſiſted <hi>with Mr.</hi> Hartley, <hi>and the ſaid Mr.</hi> Y—: <hi>That when any</hi> Conſtables <hi>have</hi> recourſe <hi>to the ſaid Office, the ſaid Sir</hi> R. B. <hi>gives Directions, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premands, and Threatens the</hi> reſpective <hi>Constables</hi> perſonating <hi>a Juſtice of the Peace, the ſaid Mr.</hi> Hartley <hi>ſpeaking but little, and being</hi> made uſe of <hi>only as a</hi> Property <hi>to ſign all the Warrants preſented by the ſaid Sir</hi> R. B. <hi>and Mr.</hi> Y—: <hi>That when the Conſtables go to Mr.</hi> Hartley, <hi>to his Habitation in</hi> London, <hi>to complain of the Irregularity of the ſaid War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,</hi> he bids them come to the ſaid Office: <hi>That we have peruſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi> 500 Warrants <hi>of Conviction, ſigned by the ſaid Mr.</hi> Hartley: <hi>That many of them are</hi> Illegal, <hi>ſome of them</hi> Nugatory and trifting, <hi>and all of them</hi> Irregular: <hi>It appears to us that ſome are</hi> convicted <hi>for ſuffering Tipling in their Houſes, that</hi> never ſold any drink; <hi>others convicted that had been</hi> dead two years before <hi>the time of Conviction: That there are about</hi> 400 Informers <hi>belonging to the ſaid Office, who carry out Warrants</hi> from the ſaid Office <hi>ready fill'd up, and</hi> tender the ſame <hi>to be ſigned</hi> to ſeveral Juſtices, <hi>who if they do (upon not being well ſatisfyed with theſe Proceedings) refuſe to ſign the ſame, are threatned to have their</hi> Names Returned <hi>into the ſaid Office. And we are of</hi> Opinion, <hi>that the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of thoſe Irregular Convictions is a great</hi> Hinderance to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Revenue of Exciſe, <hi>and a great</hi> Oppreſſion upon the People, <hi>and</hi> tends to the Ruine <hi>of most Victuallers and Alehouſe-Keepers, and</hi> makes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51003:20"/>the preſent Government uneaſie <hi>to them, as appears to us by their</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and dayly Complaints: <hi>That the Proceedings of the ſaid Office or Society is a great</hi> Affront <hi>to, and ſo reſented by the whole Commiſſion of Peace: And we are of Opinion that ſuch</hi> Warrants <hi>as are iſſued out of the ſaid Office, not executed, ſhould be ſuperceded.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>That theſe Gentlemen uſed no ordinary <hi>Diligence</hi> to find out all the Faults they could, and to amplifie and miſ-repreſent what ever appearance of any Fault they met with, as fouly and maliciouſly as they could, and as the light and frothy Wit of ſome of them could deviſe, is very apparent. But that they wilfully refuſed to uſe that Honeſt and Upright Diligence and Integrity in the Examination of the Truth of the matters referred to them, which became them, and they ought to have done, is apparent from this, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny, that they made their report <hi>ex parte;</hi> without ſending any notice to Sir <hi>R.B.</hi> or acquainting him with the particulars of their Information againſt him, although he was ready to have given them that ſatisfaction, which might have prevented, not only their ſo fouly and unworthily injuring him, but alſo their ſo unadviſedly expoſing their own Perſons, and their Unfitneſs and Unworthineſs to be entruſted with the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and the Execution of the Laws; notwithſtanding the Recommendations of the very Order of Refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which in this caſe had been juſt and reaſonable to have been obſerved.</p>
            <p>It <hi>appearing to us,</hi> ſay they, <hi>upon Oath:</hi> But whoſe Oath this was they reſolvedly conceal, and will not diſcover; or who were their Informers, ſo much as to their Brother Juſtice, who is concerned in it, and was upon the Bench moſt part of the Seſſions; notwithſtanding the ſaid Order of Referrence: Which is another great Evidence of Partiality, and little regard to Juſtice or Common Civility. And this juſtly moves thoſe Gentlemen, who know the matter of the Report to be falſe, to believe with much aſſurance that the Committee cannot produce any one Perſon of Credit, that either did, or will affirm it upon Oath in ſuch manner as they have ſet it out. And if this be ſo, how foul a Fault it is in them thus to amplifie and miſrepreſent Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations which they have received upon Oath, I leave to others to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. But in cafe they had had ſome malicious deſperate Fellow, or ſome conceited Knight of the Poſt, who could have dreſſed up his Story in this manner, is all that ſuch Men will ſay upon their Oath, preſently to be credited and ſolemnly reported? Ought not Circumſtances to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51003:20"/>be conſidered, and Probabilities be well weighed before any thing be concluded, and eſpecially in ſuch a Caſe as this? Certainly there was no ſuch diligent Examination as is pretended, and became them to have made; when what they had, and might have had on the other ſide was not regarded.</p>
            <p>That there was any ſuch Office commonly call'd Sir <hi>R. B</hi>'s <hi>Office,</hi> or any at all ſet up by him; that he or any one elſe did ever <hi>preſide</hi> at any of the Meetings of thoſe Gentlemen; that there were any <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Conſtables,</hi> more than the two before-mentioned, who had any <hi>Recourſe</hi> to that Chamber; that Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> did there <hi>perſonate a Juſtice</hi> of the Peace; that Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> was <hi>made uſe of as a Property</hi> to fign Warrants; and that he did at any time bid any Conſtable <hi>come to the ſaid Office,</hi> are all falſe, and impudent, ſcandalous Fictions, and plain Nugatory Trifles of ſome malicious, light and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Perſons. And having already ſet out the Truth of thoſe things, from whence they took their Ground, I need ſay no more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, and indeed from a due Conſideration of the Report it ſelf, it is manifeſt what Credit is to be given to their <hi>Bare Aſſerſion,</hi> that of about 500 Warrants, which they ſay they peruſed; many were <hi>Illegal,</hi> ſome <hi>Nugatory and Trifling,</hi> and all <hi>Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular,</hi> without the leaſt mention of any other Particular, than thoſe two, which I have before ſhewed, were Miſtakes (if they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Miſtakes) not of the Juſtice, but of the Informers, and beſides involuntary, and ſuch as any man might eaſily commit; Which is a ſtrong Preſumption and weighty Argument, that they had no more or greater Inſtances; eſpecially when we ſee them ſtrain their Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to multiply two ſingle Inſtances into plural Numbers. But for them to complain of Illegal, Nugatory, Trifling and Irregular! However their calling in, tearing, or ſuppreſſing ſo many Warrants under ſuch Nugatory Pretences, is that for which I think they ought not to be trifled with.</p>
            <p>The next Clauſe is true in part, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Informers did tender Warrants ready filled up to be ſigned to ſeveral Juſtices, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſign them: But it is not only falſe, but improbable that they ſhould <hi>threaten</hi> any Juſtices; and more improbable that they ſhould threaten <hi>to return their Names into</hi> any ſuch <hi>Office,</hi> which they never heard of, nor could be imagined to have any Power over them.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51003:21"/>
            <p>They conclude their Report with their Worſhip's Opinion; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>That the Multiplicity of the Convictions</hi> (which they pleaſe, to call Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, by which what they intend is noted before) <hi>is a great Hinderance to their Majeſties Revenue of Exciſe.</hi> On the Loyalty and Policy of the late Reigns! Not yet forgotten. But they forgot we have now Princes of more Magnanimity and Religion, than to ſtoop to ſo mean Policies as the Augmentation of their Revenue by the Prophanation of Religion, the Corruption of the Manners of the People, and the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Laws, which they are bound to maintain, and ſee that they be duly executed; and of more Prudence than to be ſo impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon by ſuch Pretences, ſo to recede from their Authority as well as Duty. They add:</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>And a great Oppreſſion upon the People, and tend to the Ruine of moſt Victuallers and Ale houſe keepers, and makes the preſent Government uneaſie to them.</hi> The profound Wiſdom and Goodneſs of theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen! Poſſibly ſo good Nature might extend to one ſort more, which they thought not fit, or needleſs to name, being ſufficiently compriſed among theſe. And indeed it is a plain Caſe, that the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Good Laws will always moſt certainly make any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uneaſie to thoſe, who will not otherwiſe amend their Manners. And the Neglect thereof will as certainly in time make them as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to the Government. But for ruining of any honeſt and ſober Victualler, and Ale houſe keeper by legal Convictions, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which made the Laws, were, it ſeems, of another Opinion: And we may preſume all thoſe, who all this while have never ſince thought fit to alter them, to have continued of the ſame. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe Gentlemen, who preſume thus to argue againſt the Laws, very much forget themſelves, that they were only at a Seſſions of the Peace, and not of Parliament; or elſe they would never ſo una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly have ſubſcribed to ſuch Stuff as this. But we have more of their Worſhips Opinion; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Proceedings of the ſaid Office</hi> (as they will needs call it) <hi>or Society is a great Affront to, and ſo reſented by the whole Commiſſion of the Peace.</hi> By whoſe Commiſſion, I ſuppoſe, they intend all the Juſtices in Commiſſion, and not only their own Party; and if ſo, I muſt be excuſed from giving Credit to what they ſay; for I know the contrary: And though they had muſtered all their Strength for this purpoſe, yet I am ſatisfied that there were divers very worthy Perſons upon the Bench this Seſſions, who well approved the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of thoſe Gentlemen; but not thoſe of this Committee. And had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51003:21"/>the Committee but deigned that lawful Favour or Civility to the innocent and honeſt Gentlemen concerned, which they readily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, even beyond Law, to Criminals and Offenders, they might have ſeen Cauſe to have better confuited their own Reputation, than to have expoſed it by ſo miſtaken and unworthy a Reſentment.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they conclude their Opinion, <hi>That ſuch Warrants, as are iſſued out of the ſaid Office not executed, ſhould be ſuperceded.</hi> There being no ſuch Office, it is hard to ſay what Warrants they mean: But becauſe we muſt ſuppoſe they did mean ſome, unleſs we ſuppoſe them to talk idly, we muſt underſtand all ſuch as were ſign'd by <hi>Juſtice Hartley</hi> at that Chamber. But had they been more than indeed they were, Why muſt they be ſuperceded? Certainly they would be hard put to it to find a legal and regular Anſwer; and much more to anſwer for all thoſe Warrants, which they have torn or ſuppreſs'd, very raſhly, I doubt and unadviſedly, as well as illegally.</p>
            <p>This Report, notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed (as they are pleaſed to term it) by an <hi>Order of Seſſions,</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing date the 16th. of <hi>Oct.</hi> But though the <hi>Minutes</hi> were then taken, ſomething to do there was, it ſeems, among ſome of them afterward, before they could ſettle the <hi>Order,</hi> which, though often call'd for, a Copy of it could not be had till that Day Fortnight; and by that time they had at laſt hammered it out, how agreeable to the <hi>Minutes</hi> I know not, in the Form here following:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>UPon reading the Report of Sir</hi> C.L. <hi>Sir</hi> J.S &amp;c. <hi>Juſtices of the Feace for this County, to whom it was referred, by Order of this Court of the</hi> 12th. <hi>of</hi> October <hi>inſtant, to examine, among other matters, what Inhabitants of this County have been convicted by Warrant from</hi> Ralph Hartley <hi>
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> one of their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for this County, for Tippling, expoſing Goods to Sale on the Lord's Day, or any other Offences for Prophanation thereof, whereby it</hi> appeared <hi>the ſaid Mr.</hi> Hartley <hi>hath ſigned</hi> above 500 <hi>Warrants of Conviction, many of which are illegal; and that ſome Perſons were convicted for ſuffering Tipling in their Houſes, that never ſold any Drink; others that had been dead two years before Conviction. It is</hi> thought fit and ordered <hi>by this Court, That the ſaid</hi> Report <hi>be, and it is hereby</hi> confirmed; <hi>and that all</hi> Conſtables <hi>and</hi> Headboroughs <hi>within their reſpective Diviſions in this County, do</hi> attend <hi>their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for this County,</hi> at their Petty Seſſions, <hi>to be held within their ſeveral Diviſions, with</hi> all ſuch Warrants of Conviction <hi>as now are, or ſhall hereafter come to their Hands, againſt any Perſon or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51003:22"/>Perſons, for Tipling, expoſing of Fruit, or other Goods to Sale on the Lords Day, or any Offence for Prophanation thereof; and that the ſaid Juſtices of the Peace, at their ſaid Peity Seſſions, do</hi> Summon <hi>before them the Perſons Convicted of any ſuch Offences, and the Informers, and</hi> ſuſpend the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of, or diſcharge all ſuch Warrants as they ſhall find to be illegal; and alſo to</hi> examine what Monies <hi>have been levied by Virtue of any ſuch Warrants, how the ſame hath been diſpoſed of, and to whom by Name, and by whoſe Warrant of Conviction ſuch Money hath been levied, and</hi> certifie <hi>what ſhall appear to them upon ſuch Examination to their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, at the next General Seſſions of the Peace to be held for this County.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Per Cur Harcourt.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>In the Recital in the beginning of this Order it is ſaid indeed, <hi>whereby it appeared,</hi> &amp;c. but what that was, whereby it appeared, it doth not there appear; yet they think fit and poſitively order, <hi>That the ſaid Report be,</hi> and is hereby <hi>confirmed;</hi> though that it ſelf be another Difficulty what they intend by <hi>confirmed?</hi> It was Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, which was referr'd to the Committee to examine and report; and is it fit for the Bench to confirm what perhaps may in Fact be falſe? And if it be ſo, will their Confirmation amend it? And not rather be a blemiſh upon the Proceedings of the Court, and the whole Commiſſion (as they call it) wherein are divers worthy Perſons, who were then abſent; and if they had been preſent, would doubtleſs have oppoſed and diſclaimed theſe Proceedings. Well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Gentlemen, it ſeems, they were, who were upon the Bench, and agreed to this Order; or at leaſt who have been hammering of it ever ſince, and eaſily perſwaded to call in Queſtion 500 Warrants and 500 more to that, if ſo many come to the Conſtable's hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next petty Seſſions; becauſe the Committee tell them that many of them were illegal and all irregular, without naming any one Particular for which they are ſo. In caſe ſome had been convicted for ſuffering Tipling, that never ſold Drink; and ſome who were dead two years before (which yet are ſuch ſtrains as no way become the Gravity and Integrity of a Magiſtrate) or any other miſtake had been in the Information, (which doubtleſs ſhould have been ſet out, if any ſuch could have been found,) I would know of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, whether this had made thoſe Warrants illegal or irregular? And what had been the proper Legal and Regular Courſe to have been taken, and by whom, in ſuch a Caſe?</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51003:22"/>
            <p>But of the 500 Warrants, ſuppoſe many had in truth been Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal; Were all thoſe 500 Warrants for Prophanation of the Lord's Day? Or, if they were not, were none of the reſt Illegal? If any of the reſt were illegal, why are ſuch only as were for the Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of that Day ordered to be brought in? If none of all the reſt were illegal, it is plain that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> acted commonly with good Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of what he did; and if he had erred in one or two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, thoſe might eaſily have been expreſſed in the Order. And ſince they are not, there muſt have been ſome Reaſon for it: And what more likely than that there were no ſuch as they could rely upon, and therefore reſolved upon a General Allegation, though a meer Calumny, to ſupport their Deſign to interrupt and diſcourage the Execution of theſe Laws, by an Order of Seſſions, which they found they could not do by checking and diſcouraging the Informers in private? Otherwiſe it had been certainly more proper for the Committee to have reported the particular Inſtances and Caſes wherein they had been Illegal or Irregular, and their Opinions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon with their Reaſons; and ſuch a Report might have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to have been confirmed by the Opinion of the Bench, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of particular Juſtices. But otherwiſe to require the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables to bring in all theſe Warrants to be inſpected at the petty Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, was unneceſſarily to trouble the Country, and to give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Diſſenſions and Confuſion among the Juſtices themſelves.</p>
            <p>And I deſire to know by what Law or Authority the whole Bench can order the Juſtices at the petty Seſſions, to ſummon the Perſons convicted and the Informers, (who perhaps are not known) and to ſuſpend the Execution of ſo many Warrants till they have reheard the Cauſes over again? And what Authority the Juſtices at their Petty Seſſions have to put any ſuch Trouble upon the Officers in ſuch Caſe, or upon the Informers either?</p>
            <p>But to conclude this Matter, theſe things are apparent to any one who conſiders them, from theſe Orders and Report themſelves, without more of doe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, That theſe Gentlemen, who have made all this ſtir with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any better ground, were Perſons <hi>not very well affected</hi> to the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of theſe Laws.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That that was apparently a great <hi>Cauſe, why ſo many reſorted to Mr.</hi> Hartley, with Informations, who making Conſcience of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Laws according to his Oath, heard them patiently, and gave them all convenient Diſpatch.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51003:23"/>3. That theſe Gentlemen, who were the <hi>firſt occaſion</hi> of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort and Trouble to Mr <hi>H.</hi> by wilful Neglect of their Duties, were <hi>unworthily incenſed</hi> againſt him for it, and for his honeſt conſcientious diſcharge of his.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That though they have been ſo greatly (though undeſervedly and unworthily) inceaſed againſt him, as appears by their indecent and ſcandalous treatment of him in this matter; yet have they <hi>not been able to aſſign any one particular</hi> of Illegality or Irregularity in any one Warrant, of about 500. which they ſay they have peruſed, ſigned by him. And that this is a great <hi>Demonſtration of his Juſtice,</hi> and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Behaviour in all this buſineſs, <hi>and of their Iniquity</hi> and unworthy Malice againſt him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the Report, and this Order of Seſſions to confirm it, and the matters therein contained, tend directly to the Interruption and Diſturbance, and Diſcouragement of the Execution of theſe Laws, which (as was their Duty) her Majeſty had ſpecially recommended and required to be faithfully and diligently executed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That all this is done without any particular juſt and manifeſt Reaſon; which is therefore a manifeſt and bold Contempt of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Authority.</p>
            <p>And now, upon conſideration of this whole matter, which is ſo groſs and palpable as cannot be denied, and will doubtleſs move the Indignation of all Serious and Vertuous People in the Nation, many good People will be concerned to know, whether by our Laws and Conſtitution there be no due Correction for thoſe Relicks of Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government? To which, for their Satiſfaction I can aſſure them, that there is ſufficient, and that by the ſpecial Favour and Providence of God, we have now ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſuch Judges upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it is not to be queſtion'd, but ſome effectual courſe will be taken for the due correction of thoſe bold Preſumptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws, and Inſolencies againſt her Majeſties Authority, and for a better Regulation of the Commiſſion of the Peace for this County for the future.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
